Guide to the South Africa Policy Implementation Committee records, 1984-1987
Duke University. University Archives
South Africa Policy Implementation Committee records 1984-1987
Duke University. University Archives
Duke University. Office of the President. South Africa Policy Implementation Committee.
1.4 linear feet Extent: Approx. 1,200 Items
The South Africa Policy Implementation Committee was authorized by resolution of the Board of Trustees in 1986 to implement the policies recommended by the Committee on Social Implications of Duke Stock, formed in 1985. Collection contains records relating to the operations and activities of the South Africa Policy Implementation Committee and includes correspondence, memoranda, reports, minutes, printed material, and clippings concerning apartheid and Duke University's decision to divest.
RL.01835
Language: Material in English
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the University Archives to use this collection.
Records of the University's Board of Trustees which have been existence for at least fifty years are available for scholarly research with the permission of the University Archivist. Access to records which have been in existence for less than fifty years shall be granted only by special permission, in writing, from the Board of Trustees.
Provenance
The South Africa Policy Implementation Committee records were received by the University Archives as a transfer prior to 2007.
Historical Note
Formed in 1986, the South Africa Policy Implementation Committee pursued the policies formulated by the Committee on Social Implications of Duke Stock and agreed to by the Board of Trustees. In 1985, University President Terry Sanford created the Committee on Social Implications of Duke Stock. The Committee was chaired by Law School professor Walter Dellinger, III, and composed of four students, graduate and undergraduate, six faculty members, two administrators, and two Trustees.
On May 3, 1986 the Board of Trustees, at the recommendation of the Committee on Social Implications of Duke Stock, voted to sell all holdings of companies doing business in South Africa if that nation's system of apartheid was not ended by January 1, 1987.
The Board's vote in support of divestment followed more than a year of campus activism focusing on apartheid and University investments in South Africa.
Collection Overview
Contains material pertaining to the activities of the South Africa Policy Implementation Committee. The collection contains rosters, minutes, and reports of the Committee as well as correspondence and memoranda concerning Duke's policy toward and financial relationships with corporations with operations in South Africa during apartheid. Correspondence between University President H. Keith H. Brodie and representatives of corporations such as International Business Machines, Mcgraw-Hill, Inc., Texaco, Inc., American Express Company, R.J. Reynolds/Nabisco, Inc., and Cocoa-Cola Company documents corporate reaction to Duke's decision to divest. Memoranda, minutes, reports, and rosters of the Committee on Social Implications of Duke Stock are also present.
Throughout the collection are clippings and other printed material addressing social, political, and economic conditions in South Africa, policies adopted by other universities and colleges toward South Africa, and reports and studies relating to the feasibility, appropriateness, and potential consequences of divestment.
Subject Headings
These are searchable subject entries for this collection. Performing a search on these subjects in the Duke University Libraries online catalog will bring up other related research materials.
Anti-apartheid movements -- United States -- History -- 20th century; Anti-apartheid movements -- North Carolina -- Durham; Apartheid -- South Africa; Apartheid -- Economic aspects -- South Africa; Brodie, H. Keith H. (Harlow Keith Hammond), 1939-.; Corporate divestiture -- South Africa; Duke University. Office of the President; Sanford, Terry, 1917-1998
Related Material
Eisinger, Jana, The Divestment Campaign at Duke University: Stepchild of the Civil Rights Movement
Duke University Archives/David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
H. Keith H. Brodie, President, records, 1963-1994
Duke University Archives/David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Records and Papers of Terry Sanford, 1945-1998
Duke University Archives/David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Terry Sanford Papers, 1926-1996
Duke University Archives/David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Student Activism Reference Collection, 1934-[ongoing]
Duke University Archives/David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Ron Grunwald Papers, 1973-1980
Duke University Archives/David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Detailed Description of Collection
- Container List, 2 boxes
  - Administrative, 1985-1987, (4 folders) (Box 1)
  - Barr, Graham (staff): notes and miscellaneous. 1985-1986, undated
  - Clippings and articles, 1984-1986
  - PIC mailings and handouts, 1986-1987
  - Corporate response to May 3, 1986 resolution on divestment (A-Q), 1986-1987, (3 folders)
  - Corporate response to May 3, 1986 resolution on divestment (R-Z), 1986-1987 (Box 2)
  - Letters and lists of recipients of same, 1986
  - Corporate responses to Marty [Martin T. November] (Pres. Associated Students of Duke University), 1985
  - Other Universities, Policies of, 1985-1986, (2 folders)
  - Responses from other colleges, 1986